in this video i'm going to teach you the
very basics to editing a video inside of
final cut pro 10 so if you've never used
the software before and you're just
unfamiliar with it this is the perfect
video for you i'm going to walk you step
by step on how to start editing your
videos you got to just press record hey
guys my name is normal now if you
haven't seen the first video to this
this is actually a part two video click
the link in the description and actually
go watch that one first because i show
you how to import your footage how to
organize everything how to back up your
footage as well as just get familiar
with these different windows and
different things that are going on
inside of the software now in this video
i'm gonna focus on the editing aspect so
let's just get right into it and start
editing a youtube video so i have nine
clips in my events folder right here and
i'm gonna drag all of these onto my
timeline i'm holding down shift and
select this last one i'm just going to
simply drag those and now i have all my
videos inside of my project i'm going to
zoom in a little bit here so i can see
what's going on to do that you can hit
command plus button or if you hit
command minus button this is going to
zoom out now editing is as simple as
removing clips and keeping the good
stuff so that's what we're going to do
first we're going to go through and
start removing some of the pieces that
we don't want in our final video so to
hit play so far on my video i'll hit the
space bar i'm just looking at the camera
kind of getting ready to talk and if i
zoom in on this clip right here you see
these audio waveforms down here this is
when i start talking and this is when i
want the video to start when i actually
start saying stuff also you might notice
there's this black vignetting on these
corners on this camera i'm going to show
you how to fix that how to kind of crop
in a little bit we'll do that next but
first this is what you're going to use
most of the time which is your blade
tool to pull up your blade tool you can
go over here and you can select the
blade or you could hit b but this is
kind of your tool so you have select you
can trim position range selection but i
just like to learn these shortcuts and
so i will hit b and you can see right
here now my cursor is a blade all you
have to do is select where you want to
make your cut and when you click on that
you can see that there's now a splice
right in between these videos so now we
have one cut in the video kind of making
it two videos so we can select this
first part and if we hit delete now at
the beginning of this video starts when
i start talking let's go to the end of
this clip and do the same thing over
here so i'm talking and this is where
i'm going to end it now if you hit
command b this is going to make a cut
for you right where your playhead is and
so this right here is the playhead so
where your playhead is is where it's
going to start playing your video so
with over there hit command b and this
is what happened i'll select the second
half of the clip and i will delete that
now that right there is a big piece of
editing just kind of getting rid of the
parts that you don't want and keeping
all the good stuff another thing you can
do here if you want to extend this clip
or maybe shorten it is hover over the
end of the clip and you're going to see
this trim tool now if you hold down if
you click and hold down you can drag
this to the left to start cutting off
more of this clip on the left if you
want to extend it you can drag it to the
right now if i want to do the same thing
on the right clip i'm going to slightly
move it to the right and now you see
that bracket has flipped now this means
i am trimming this right clip so i can
extend it to the left but this red
marker lets me know this is the
beginning of the clip so i'm going to
start cutting everything out that i
don't want and i want it to start right
there let's bring this clip back and
that is allowing you to trim those so
that you can extend them shorten them
lengthen them do what you want with that
i use that tool a whole lot as well now
let's say i want this clip actually to
go first before this very first clip all
you have to do is select the clip you
want to move you can drag it and we're
going to drag that right in front and
now everything kind of snaps into place
now this clip is going to play first and
this clip is now going to play second
now let's say we want to add an effect
over here we have our effects window and
let's say we want to add the camcorder
so i'm going to drag that onto this clip
here and now you're going to see that we
have this camcorder effect just by
dragging that now if i select this clip
over here in the inspector tool we can
mess with the amount of this effect
being added we'll leave that at 100. you
can change the text to whatever you want
to say let's say think the size all this
stuff is adjustable so if you ever want
to adjust something go over here into
the effects tab make sure you have your
effect selected and then you can mess
with some of these effects now let's add
a transition so i'm going to go over to
my transitions by clicking this and we
are going to let's say this circle one
we are going to drag this right in
between these two clips now let's play
it through and see how it looks
so it's pretty cool but let's say i want
to speed it up and make it a faster
transition all you need to do is trim
and shorten up that transition so with a
trim tool just like we were making a
clip shorter we're going to use this to
make our transition sorter so with the
bracket facing the right way to the left
we know that we are selecting this
transition so we are going to bring that
in and that brings in both sides for us
now it's a quicker transition and if you
want to make it extra long you can drag
that out and this now has your
transition being extra long
now let's say you want to move the
transition a little bit to the left or
the right so it starts earlier or maybe
it starts later if you hover over the
middle you can actually move this
transition let's say we want it to start
sooner this is going to cut off what we
were just having but let's say we wanted
to cut off that anyways that's how you
can move the transition within the clip
to play earlier or later let's say we
like it right here but we don't want all
this dead space all you need to do is
hit b to bring up your blade tool we are
going to cut right there then we're
going to delete this clip and now it's
going to start when i start talking all
right let's get rid of this vignette
that i was telling you guys about the
dark corners all you got to do is crop
in so with your clip selected if you go
right here we are going to change this
from trim to crop now i can actually
crop in on my clip so i'm going to make
sure that this vignette is not showing
by zooming in a bit and then we are
going to reposition where we want it
when we're done we're going to hit done
now we've actually cropped in on the
image so that we're not seeing the
vignetting and you can crop in on any
clip i use this a lot to kind of crop in
on my face crop it back out so this is a
great tool to use and to know how to use
now if we want to mess with the audio
and make the audio louder on this
specific clip we can hover over this
line right here if we hover over this
line we are going to see 0.0 db this is
the standard the neutral place for your
audio to be at so as you import any sort
of audio as you import any sort of video
it's going to start at 0 db you can then
add plus 2 plus 12 db minus 12 db you
can mess around and add or take away
from the volume so we are going to
increase the volume i'm simply just
going to drag up this line right here
and this is going to actually boost up
those waveforms you can see that now it
says 5 db and if you don't have your
audio waveforms right here all you got
to do is select this and this is going
to bring them up for you so now when i
play my clip it's going to be louder
than it was before and if i want to
completely silence it i can bring that
to zero you can see there's no audio
happening right here and then i can
bring the audio back up i'm like okay i
want it right around
9 db perfect this is exactly where i
want it and that's how you can adjust
the volume now if we want to add text up
here we have our test and generator so
i'm going to select this we have titles
and we have generators generators are
kind of like backgrounds is how i would
explain them so one i use a lot is just
a custom which is a color and then from
here we can change the color to whatever
we want so let's say we want the color
to be white i'll drag this like that now
i have a white background and i can add
text to this and so we'll go over to
titles now these different titles have
different effects we can see this one is
dramatic and if i hover over from left
to right we're gonna see kind of the
effect that it does and if you like one
you can simply drag it onto your clip
clearly it's a white text over white
background so we can't see it so what
we'll do is first let's change the face
which is going to be the color and so
we're going to hit show and we are going
to change the color to let's change it
to a blue now if you want to change your
text you can just double click on title
and this is going to highlight
everything for you now we have this text
bubble popped up so we'll change this to
think media and now let's play this
through to see how it looks
now the one i typically use is just a
custom and this is just your basic text
so let's change this text to black
and now up here we have this text so we
can change this to think media we can
change the font if we want you can move
around by dragging this here you can
also change the font size mess with any
of the properties all under here under
this properties tab back on the timeline
if we just want to delete a clip i'm
like okay i don't really want this in
there you can select the whole thing you
can delete this and then up here if you
want to use it again you can bring it
back you can see that there's an orange
underlined this means i'm using the clip
right now on my timeline this makes it
really easy to see the clips that you
haven't used yet and so i can hover over
it and see if i want to bring that back
in so if you delete something in your
project it's still going to be there in
your event and then from there you can
just bring it back into your project if
you'd like now if you aren't seeing
these orange lines all you need to do is
go to view go to browser and make sure
that used media ranges is selected now
in order to use some music let's import
it into final cut pro first so we're
going to right click right here and
we're gonna hit import media i have a
song on my desktop so i'm gonna select
that song and then hit import selected
from here i'm gonna drag this entire
song down here onto my timeline we can
do the same thing with audio that we can
with video so if we want to trim this
then we can do that if we want to lower
the audio then we can definitely do that
by bringing that down i'll then drag
this to the beginning of the project and
then if i want to fade in the audio so
it doesn't start abruptly there is a
little ball right here and if you drag
that to the right this is going to be a
fade in for your music and you can also
do this on videos by just dragging these
to the right this is going to fade in
your audio so that doesn't start
abruptly but it just fades in you can
also fade out your audio by doing the
same thing on the other end now that
right there is just the tip of the
iceberg it's the very basics of editing
if you want to learn more about audio
editing or best export settings for your
video then click on the screen and check
out our playlist with our final cut pro
10 tutorials and i'll see you guys in
the next video
[Music]